Guide to the Hugh Hubbard Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Hugh Hubbard Papers
1943-1974
RG 137
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(15 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of Hubbard. Hugh W. Hubbard was an American missionary serving in North China under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
Hubbard, Hugh W.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Hubbard family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Hugh Hubbard was born in Turkey of missionary parents. He was educated in Switzerland and received a B.A. from Amherst College, from which he also later received a D.D. In 1908 Hubbard accepted a short term appointment under the YMCA to Tientsin, China, where he served as a teacher and athletic coach. There he met Mabel Ellis, who was serving under the Women's Board of Missions. Returning to the U.S., Hugh attended Oberlin Seminary, married Mabel Ellis, and returned to China in 1913 under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. The Hubbards had four children.
A 1959 tribute to the Hubbards describes their mission work in China as follows:"Assigned to Paoting, the Hubbards began at once to seek for more effective ways of carrying the Good News into all areas of life throughout that station's exceptionally large rural field. Some years later it was the marked success of literacy campaigns in the Paoting field which led Dr. James Yen of "Thousand Character" fame to select one of its county seats as the headquarters of the Mass Education Movement. "The Christian Farmer," a magazine for new literates, was another achievement, as was the North China Christian Rural Service Union, later described by the Agricultural Missions Foundation as the most significant advance in rural evangelism in a quarter of a century. The National Christian Council requisitioned Hugh's services for a time to promote nation-wide literacy efforts; and the Fan Family Village Experiment in evangelism was showing great promise when interrupted by the Japanese invasion of 1937. Pearl Harbor caught Dr. Hubbard serving as Executive Secretary of the Church and Missions. But two years of life in an internment camp only gave their talents for leadership opportunities of a different sort. The Hubbards had barely returned from a post-war furlough when in 1947 Hugh was again requisitioned, this time by UNESCO, to direct for two years a pilot project in Fundamental Education. The Hubbards were the last American Board family to leave China after Communist control was established, staying by under increasing limitations unitl April 1952...."
"Hugh was an ardent hunter, one of the best tennis players in North China, and as an ornithologists published in collaboration wtih Dr. George Wilder the best handbook on the birds of North China. Both Hubbards had exceptional command of the Chinese language, written and spoken."
Hugh and Mabel Hubbard worked for the American Board Office of Communication following their return from China. They retired in January, 1958. Additional biographical documentation can be found in Series II.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Biographical Documentation
III. Writings
IV. Subject Files
Though a collection of this size cannot do full justice to the wide range of activities undertaken by Hugh Hubbard during his many years of service in China, the letters, writings, and collected material contained here provide an interesting glimpse into his life and work. These papers are complemented by papers of other American Board missionaries held by the Yale Divinity Library, as well as by the American Board archives on microfilm, and its periodical, pamphlet, and report literature.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Biographical Documentation
III. Writings
IV. Subject Files
Missions -- China; Hubbard, Hugh W.; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- China
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Hubbard, Chauncey (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hubbard, Crescens and Julia (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hubbard, Dave and Sterl (Grandsons) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hubbard, Emma Rose (sister) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hubbard, Emma Spenser (mother) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hubbard, Gladys and Lloyd (Swift) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hubbard, Gladys and Lloyd (Swift) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Swift, Larry and Marilee (grandson) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hubbard, Mabel (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hubbard, Martin (nephew) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hubbard, Nan (Sister-in-law) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hubbards (Peel, Faith, Spenser, etc.) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Hubbard, Theodore and Ruth (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Hubbard, Ward and Arline (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Swift, Alan (grandson) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Swift, Eric (grandson) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Swift, Jon (grandson) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hubbard, general family, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence
    - Circular letters from Hubbard family while serving in China under UNESCO and ABCFM, including "The Watchman", 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Auburndale Congregational Church (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Babcock, Everitt (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Baily, Harold -- Ballou, Earle (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Barnes -- Barnett (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Barron -- Bedikian (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bliss -- Boorman (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Birge -- Blemker (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Bostelmann -- Bowen (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Boynton -- Briggs (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Brown -- Butts (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Cady -- Carleton (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Cary -- Chandler (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Chang (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Chapman -- Christie (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Chuan -- Clack (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Clarement -- Cochran (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Commonwealth -- Cooley (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cooper -- Crossley (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - C misc. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Darymple -- Davis (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Denison -- Dewar (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Dewick -- Dodd (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Donaldson -- Dow (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Downs -- Durgin (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Dutton (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Eddy -- Ellis (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Ellis (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Fairbank -- Frazier (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Ferrell -- Fitzgerald (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Fingerhut -- Fong (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Foto -- Fowle (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Franzen -- F (misc) (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Gallup -- Goodrich (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Guest -- G (misc.) (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Galt (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Goodsell -- Grant (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Greater -- Gregorian (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Gregory -- Gulick (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Groetzinger (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Haband -- Harrison (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Harvey -- Hausske (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Hayes (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Hayford -- Hazleton (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Hebert -- Helfferrich (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Hemmingsen (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Hemmingsen (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Hemmingsen, W and H (Box 3, Folder 67-70)
    - Hemmingsen -- Hessel (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Hewlett -- Hinkhouse (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Hock -- Holmes (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Hood -- Hoskins (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Heath, Harvey and Leola (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Huggins (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Hughes -- Hyer (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Writings: Hunter, J.A. (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Correspondence: Hunter, J.A. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Hunter, J.A., includes pictures (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Ih-Chi -- Isaacs (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Jack -- Jacques (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - deJaegher, incl. photos (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Jenkins, Alfred (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - deJaegher -- Judd (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - J (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Kandle -- Kang (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Kattwinkel -- Kees (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Keitel (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Kelly -- Kenco (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Kennedy -- Kung (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Lamb -- Leham (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Leiper -- Leonard (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Lerrigo -- Li (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Lien -- Long (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Lord (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Loucks (Box 4, Folder 97-101)
    - Luidens (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Lovatt -- Lung (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Misc. L (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Ma -- (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - MacDonald -- Mackenzie (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Mackey -- Malcom (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Malcom (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Manchester -- Manny (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Martin (Box 4, Folder 110-111)
    - Massachusets -- Matthews (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Matthews (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - McClure -- McGlamery (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - McMurty -- Medlicott (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Melcher (Box 4, Folder 116-117)
    - Menge -- Mersereau (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Merwin -- Meyer (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Meyers -- Mills (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Miller -- Mook (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Montgomery -- Moore (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Moriwaki -- Moulton (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Mulholland -- Myrick (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Najaka -- Newsweek (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - New York -- Nitta (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - North -- Nystrom (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Oberlin -- Olds (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Orr -- Owyang (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Parker -- Peabody (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Peake -- Pennsylvania (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Perkins -- Phillips (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Planned Parenthood (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Pikher -- Prien (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Price (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Pyke -- Pyle (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Rahill -- Rankin (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Rawlinson -- Read (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Reader's -- Rueling (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Reitlinger -- Riggs (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Riley -- Rural (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Robinson, Harold and Mary (Box 5, Folder 142-144)
    - Robinson, Hugh L., MD (Box 5, Folder 145-146)
    - Sanderson -- Severance (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Severinghaus (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Severinghaus (Box 5, Folder 149-150)
    - Severinghaus, Les (Box 5, Folder 151-152)
    - Sharp -- Shaw (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Shek -- Shield (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Smith (Box 5, Folder 155-156)
    - Smith -- Stern (Box 5, Folder 157)
    - Stowe, David and Virginia (Box 5, Folder 158)
    - Stockwell -- Stowe (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Stowers -- Swart (Box 5, Folder 160)
    - Taylor -- Thomson (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Thomson (Box 5, Folder 162)
    - Thornton (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - Thurston -- Todd (Box 5, Folder 164)
    - Tong-- Typer (Box 5, Folder 165)
    - Ulanga -- United (Box 5, Folder 166)
    - Misc. (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Miscellaneous M's (Box 5, Folder 168)
    - Miscellaneous Papers and Photos (Box 5, Folder 169)
    - Van Kirk (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Vetch -- Verink (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Vetch, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 172-177)
    - Wilder, Durand (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - Walburn, Wantabe (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Wheatcroft, White (Box 6, Folder 180)
    - Whitney -- Wilder (Box 6, Folder 181)
    - Wilder, T.S. (Box 6, Folder 182-186)
    - Wilder -- Wilson (Box 6, Folder 187)
    - Wimer -- Wylie (Box 6, Folder 188)
    - Yale -- Yen (Box 6, Folder 189)
    - Yeranian (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - Yinson -- Yu-Shan (Box 6, Folder 191)
    - Zia -- Zinsmaster (Box 6, Folder 192)
- Biographical Documentation, Series II
  - Collected Autobiographical Materials
    - Amherst College, MA, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Collected Materials (Box 7, Folder 194-196)
    - Family Information (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Health and Medical (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Insurance (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - Property Lists (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Last Will and Testimony (Box 7, Folder 201)
    - UCBFWM Financial Information (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - Wells Hubbard Memorial Fund (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - UCBFWM Conditional Gift (Box 7, Folder 204)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 205)
  - Autobiographical writings
    - Introduction to Autobiography (Box 7, Folder 206)
    - Writings (Box 7, Folder 207-208)
- Writings, Series III
  - Communism and Religion (Box 8, Folder 209)
  - Essays: Miscellaneous topics (Box 8, Folder 210)
  - Misc. Notes (Box 8, Folder 211)
  - Missionary Work in China (Box 8, Folder 212)
  - North China Mission History (Box 8, Folder 213)
  - Poems (Box 8, Folder 214)
  - Prayers (Box 8, Folder 215)
  - Public Addresses (Box 8, Folder 216)
  - Sermons and Speeches (Box 8, Folder 217)
  - Rural Literature (Box 8, Folder 218)
- Subject Files, Series IV
  - Re. Birds
    - Agreements Birdbook (Box 9, Folder 219)
    - Avian Drugs (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Bird Book Notes (Box 9, Folder 221)
    - Birds from Desk, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 222-224)
    - Book Draft (Box 9, Folder 225)
    - Chinese Birds Names (Box 9, Folder 226)
    - (Wilder and Hubbard) corrections (Box 9, Folder 227)
    - Bird Book - Vetch (Box 9, Folder 228)
    - First Copy (Box 9, Folder 229)
    - Foreword: "Observations" by Hubbard (Box 9, Folder 230)
    - Glossary (Box 9, Folder 231)
    - Index -- Migration Notes (Box 9, Folder 232)
    - Migration notes (Box 9, Folder 233)
    - "List of the Birds of the Chihli Province" by G.D. Wilder and H.W. Hubbard (Box 10, Folder 234)
    - Ornithology (Box 10, Folder 235)
    - Outline: "Adventures" by G. Wilder (Box 10, Folder 236)
    - Wilder's Repatriation Trip, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 237)
    - Wilder's Repatriation Trip, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 238)
    - Bird Collection, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 239)
  - China Materials
    - Agricultural Missions Tribute (Box 11, Folder 240)
    - Chinese Newspaper Articles (Box 11, Folder 241)
    - Chinese Calendars (Box 11, Folder 242)
    - Chinese Nationalism (Box 11, Folder 243)
    - China Notes, 1967-1970 (Box 11, Folder 244)
    - China Notes, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 245)
    - Foreign Claims Settlement Commission: War losses claim (Box 11, Folder 246)
    - Foreign Claims Settlement (Box 11, Folder 247-249)
    - Kiangsi, Rural Construction (Box 11, Folder 250)
    - Music (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - North China Rural Service Union (Box 11, Folder 252-253)
    - Newsletters - American Board, 1949-1952 (Box 12, Folder 254-255)
    - North China Mission History (Box 12, Folder 256)
    - Photograph (Box 12, Folder 257)
    - Play- "Easter Story" (Box 12, Folder 258)
    - Play- "The Two Roads" (Box 12, Folder 259)
    - Rural Church (Box 12, Folder 260)
    - Slides: Misc. (Box 12, Folder 261)
    - United Nations report, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 262)
    - Vadala Gift (Box 12, Folder 263)
    - Village Reconstruction (Box 12, Folder 264)
    - "When East Meets West" - Christopher Ma (Box 12, Folder 265)
  - Filmstrip scripts
    - Blakney, C.P. (Box 13, Folder 266)
    - Bwerudza, H (Box 13, Folder 267)
    - Dettman, Paul "Waters Break Though" (Box 13, Folder 268)
    - Dettman, Paul "The Making of Indian Pastors" (Box 13, Folder 269)
    - Dettman, Paul "Madurai Pastor" (Box 13, Folder 270)
    - Dettman, Paul "The Story of Sunder" (Box 13, Folder 271)
    - Dewar, Mary (Box 13, Folder 272)
    - Donaldson, John (Box 13, Folder 273)
    - Dudley, Raymond (Box 13, Folder 274)
    - Fairbank, R (Box 13, Folder 275)
    - Gillett, Clarence and Marion (Box 13, Folder 276)
    - Grant, Robert (Box 13, Folder 277)
    - Griesy, Paul (Box 13, Folder 278)
    - Gulick, Leeds (Box 13, Folder 279)
    - Hayes, Lois and Malcolm (Box 13, Folder 280)
    - Heinrich, John (Box 13, Folder 281)
    - Houston, Lyda (Box 13, Folder 282)
    - Kaetzel, Sam and Rika (Box 13, Folder 283)
    - Lord, Charles (personal report) (Box 13, Folder 284)
    - Lord, Charles "The Prodigal Son" (Box 13, Folder 285)
    - Lord, Charles "The Good Samaritan" (Box 13, Folder 286)
    - Lord, Charles "Joseph and His Faith" (Box 13, Folder 287)
    - Markham, Robin "Joao's Life at School" (Box 13, Folder 288)
    - Markham, Robin "Missionary to His People" (Box 13, Folder 289)
    - Markham, Robin and Vicky (Box 13, Folder 290)
    - Markham, Robin "A Student's Life at Currie" (Box 13, Folder 291)
    - McGowan, Robert "A Doctor's Adventures in Angola" (Box 13, Folder 292)
    - Munson, Frederick "India, A Land of Opportunity" (Box 13, Folder 293)
    - Nicholson, Oline (Box 13, Folder 294)
    - Nishimura, Sugao (Box 13, Folder 295)
    - Riggs, Dr. and Mrs. Edward (Box 13, Folder 296)
    - Robertson, Grace (Box 13, Folder 297)
    - Scott, Lavinia (Box 13, Folder 298)
    - Shepard, Fred and Alice (Box 13, Folder 299)
    - Sell "Building for Tomorrow" (Box 13, Folder 300)
    - Shepard, Fres and Alice (Box 13, Folder 301)
    - Stetson, Dr. and Mrs. Kirk (Box 13, Folder 302)
    - Swift, Lloyd (Box 13, Folder 303)
    - Summerville, Harriet (Box 13, Folder 304)
    - Terpstra, Chester (Box 13, Folder 305)
    - Thelin, Guy and Betty (Box 14, Folder 306)
    - Thomas, Margaret and Ross (Box 14, Folder 307)
    - Weeber, Carolyn (Box 14, Folder 308)
    - Whitener, Sterling (Box 14, Folder 309)
    - Introductions (Box 14, Folder 310)
    - "Peking the Beautiful" (Box 14, Folder 311)
    - Script lists (Box 14, Folder 312)
    - Bible Stories (Box 14, Folder 313)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 14, Folder 314)
  - Stamps
    - Correspondence, 1960-1973 (Box 15, Folder 315-316)
    - Cross, Rowland (Box 15, Folder 317)
    - Kauder, Warrin G., 1967-1972 (Box 15, Folder 318-319)
    - re: The China Stamp Society, "The China Clipper" (Box 15, Folder 320)